Dorchester, Boston, Mass. Second Church records, 1770-1991.
Congregational Library Archives
- Incorporated churches, 1888 1991; 1888-1991; 31 Items
  - Harvard Congregational Church, 1888 1991; 1888-1940, 1988-1991; 18 Items
    This sub-series contains records from the Harvard Congregational Church which was incorporated by Second Church. Included are records related to the Ladies Benevolent Society, Women's Benevolent Society, Reading Circle, Harvard Helpers, Women's Club, financial information and a treasurer's book.
    Historical Note
    Harvard Congregational Church was first opened in 1888 and lasted until 1926 when it was incorporated into Second Church. Not much else is known about the church besides its operational dates.
    Ministers
    Daniel Temple Torrey 1888-1892
    William Thomas Beale 1899-1908
    Charles Foster Weeden 1909-1916
    - Ladies Benevolent Society records, 1888 1892; 1888-1892 (Box 20, Volume 1)
    - Harvard Congregational Church Treasurer's Book, 1888 1916; 1888-1916 (Box 19, Volume 3)
    - Harvard Church Women's Benevolent Society records, 1893 1902; 1893-1902 (Box 21, Volume 5)
    - Harvard Church Women's Benevolent Society records, 1902 1908; 1902-1908 (Box 21, Volume 6)
    - Harvard Church Women's Benevolent Society records, 1909 1914; 1909-1914 (Box 21, Volume 7)
    - Harvard Church Reading Circle, 1910 (Box 21, Volume 15)
    - Harvard Church Reading Circle, 1911 1913; 1911-1913 (Box 21, Volume 16)
    - Harvard Church Reading Circle records, 1915-10 1916-09; October 1915 - September 1916 (Box 31, Folder 24)
    - Harvard Helpers, 1915 1919; 1915-1919 (Box 31, Folder 23)
    - Harvard Church Women's Benevolent Society records, 1915 1920; 1915-1920 (Box 21, Volume 8)
    - Harvard Church Reading Circle records, 1916-10 1919-12; October 1916 - December 1919 (Box 31, Folder 25)
    - Harvard Church Reading Circle records, 1920 1921; 1920-1921 (Box 31, Folder 26)
    - Women's Club records, 1920 1940; 1920-1940 (Box 20, Volume 20)
    - Harvard Church Reading Circle records, 1922 1924-10; 1922 - October 1924 (Box 31, Folder 27)
    - Harvard Congregational Church Cash Book, 1988 1991; 1988-1991 (Box 19, Volume 2)
    - Harvard Congregational Church Blueprints, undated (Box 25, Folder 81)
    - Duplicate of Original Charter, undated (Box 25, Folder 29)
    - Harvard Church Reading Circle records, undated (Box 31, Folder 28)
  - Central Congregational Church, 1902 1973; 1902-1973; 13 Items
    This sub-series contains records from the Central Congregational Church which was incorporated by Second Church. Included is information on the standing committee, treasurer's records, by-laws, meeting minutes, annual meeting minutes, correspondences, finances, real estate information and dissolution of the church.
    The church has its origins in the work of Mr. Bumpus, a city missionary who was working with Second Church and identified a need for a church around Field's Corner. The first preaching service of this initiative was done by Reverend E. N. Packard on October 11th, 1885. First minister to work at Central Congregational was Reverend T. J. Voluntine and we was there until November 1st, 1887. Following that, Reverend C. C. Kellogg became Pastor. The group voted on January 23rd, 1888 to form an official organization. On March 15th of the same year, fifty-four members formed Bethany Congregational Church. In May, the churches official "Building Fund" started after an initial donation of two dollars. They would purchase land facing Adams Street and in December 1890 the plans for a building were adopted. The name of the church would be officially changed to the Central Congregational Church on July 19th, 1891. Reverend Kellogg ended his ministry on October 31st, 1892 and was replaced by Reverend Perley B. Davis. After some troubling years it was decided to sell the church building to Emanual Baptist Church on November 15th, 1898. Afterwards, the group worshiped at Wynona Hall. On November 1st, 1899 Reverend Davis resigned and Reverend George H. Flint was elected to take over. It would take Reverend Flint and Central Congregational Church about a year to find a new piece of land. That land would be purchased on February 14th, 1901. At the annual meeting in 1904, the group voted to erect a new church. The cornerstone of the new church was laid on May 22nd, 1906. The opening address was made by Reverend Arthur Little of Second Church. By the time of the 25th Annual Meeting, membership had risen to 274. Reverend Clinton J. Taft began his pastorate on September 1st, 1915. During this time the church worked alongside the campaign of Billy Sunday. Reverend Taft worked until September 20th, 1918. The next pastor would be reverend Albert F. Pierce who began his work on February 2nd, 1919. Some of his highlights include installing a new bell, building the parsonage and burning the church mortgage. Reverend Pierce would resign on September 1st, 1919. Dr. Simpson ran the pulpit until Reverend Lester E. Evans began his pastorate on January 1st, 1922. At the 40th anniversary of the church, many former members and others were present. Reverend Evans left to become pastor in Haverhill, Mass on November 1st, 1929. Reverend Warren P. Landers served in an interim status for Central Congregational Church until Reverend Norman Kind started on December 22, 1929. At this juncture, the available historical information of the church dries up until 1973, when the church officially dissolved into the Second Church.
    T. J. Volentine July 1, 1886 - November 1, 1887
    C. C. Kellogg November 1, 1887 - October 31, 1892
    Perley B. Davis November 1, 1892 - November 1, 1899
    George H. Flint November 1, 1899 - November 29th, 1914
    Edward C. Porter (Interim) exact dates unknown
    Clinton J. Taft September 1, 1915 - September 20, 1918
    Albert F. Pierce February 2, 1919 - September 1, 1919
    Dr. Simpson (Interim) exact dates unknown
    Lester E. Evans January 1, 1922 - November 1, 1929
    Norman King December 22, 1929 - unknown
    Bibliography
    "Golden Anniversary History." Central Congregational Church 50th Anniversary. Written by Mrs. Fred W. Connolly. 1938.
    - Central Congregational Church Standing Committee, 1902 1915; 1902-1915 (Box 18, Volume 7)
    - Central Congregational Church Treasurer's records, 1921 1927; 1921-1927 (Box 19, Volume 1)
    - Central Congregational Church By-Laws, October 23, 1929 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Central Congregational Church Meeting Minutes, 1932 1939; 1932-1939 (Box 18, Volume 8)
    - Central Congregational Church Standing Committee records, 1939 1953; 1939-1953 (Box 18, Volume 9)
    - Central Congregational Church Committee records, 1939 1963; 1939-1963 (Box 18, Volume 10)
    - Central Congregational Church Annual Meeting Minutes, 1954 1963; 1954-1963 (Box 18, Volume 11)
    - Annual Report of Treasurer Central Congregational Church, 1960-05-01 1961-04-30; May 1, 1960 - April 30, 1961 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Central Congregational Church correspondences, 1962 1973; 1962, 1971-1973 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Central Congregational Church Finances and Receipts, 1966 1972; 1966-1972 (Box 19, Volume 7)
    - Boston Real Estate Taxes Central Congregational Church, 1968 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Dissolution of Central Congregational Church, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Dissolution of the Central Congregational Church, undated (Box 30, Folder 19)
- Events, 1900 1985; 1900-1985; 13 Items
  This series contains records related to events held by Second church and include plays, birthdays, anniversaries, picnics, a Veteran's Day celebration, Children's Day service and the Forefathers' Sunday.
  - Watch Meeting to Welcome New Century, December 31, 1900 (Box 31, Folder 69)
  - Historical Leaflet for Forefathers' Sunday, December 17, 1922 (Box 31, Folder 70)
  - Magda: A Biblical Drama, 1925 (Box 31, Folder 71)
  - 134th Birthday of Church, 1939 (Box 31, Folder 72)
  - "Living Pictures" Rehearsal, 1941 1966; 1941-1966 (Box 31, Folder 73)
  - 150th, 175th and 180th Anniversaries, 1955 1985; 1955, 1980, 1985 (Box 25, Folder 56)
  - 150th Anniversary of Second Parish Incorporation, June 20, 1957 (Box 31, Folder 74)
  - Children's Day Service, 1968 1973; 1968, 1973 (Box 31, Folder 75)
  - Church Picnic Reservations, June 14, 1969 (Box 31, Folder 76)
  - Loyalty Month, 1981-10 1981-11; October - November 1981 (Box 31, Folder 77)
  - Veteran's Day, 1982 (Box 31, Folder 78)
  - Annual Report Night, undated (Box 31, Folder 79)
  - Hidden Talents: A Play, undated (Box 31, Folder 80)